Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Humanitarian Agenda 2015, 2004 -- 2010; UA197.001; 22 Digital Object(s)
    - Taking Sides or Saving Lives: Existential Choices for the Humanitarian Enterprise in Iraq: Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Iraq Country Study, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00008; Hansen, Greg
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; Iraq War, 2003-; Coalition Provisional Authority; International Committee of the Red Cross; International Federation of Red Cross & Red Crescent Societies; Multi-National Force-Iraq; United Nations; UN. Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs
    - Coming to Terms with the Humanitarian Imperative in Iraq: Humanitarian Agenda 2015 Briefing Paper, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00009; Hansen, Greg
      Paper dated January, 2007. Highlighting major changes in the context in Iraq and rapid deterioration of the humanitarian situation, this brief report summarizes an Iraq country study to be issued in final form later this month as part of the Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power and Perceptions (HA 2015) initiative, an independent research project of the Feinstein International Center, Tufts University. Following a series of observations about how humanitarianism is currently perceived in Iraq, this report highlights findings regarding the operational environment, donor environment, and strategic policy environment. The interviews conducted comprise a valuable compilation of field-based evidence, provided at a time of mounting access difficulties and diminishing awareness of the situation on the ground. In addition to extensive interviews, the report draws heavily upon work conducted in the region and the regular monitoring of developments by the Humanitarianism and War Project in 2004 and 2005, thus spanning a three-year period.2 It concludes with 20 recommendations for the UN system, Red Cross / Red Crescent Movement, humanitarian NGOs, the NGOs Coordinating Committee in Iraq (NCCI) and donors.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; Iraq War, 2003-; United Nations; UN Assistance Mission for Iraq; UN. Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs
    - Coming to Terms with the Humanitarian Imperative in Iraq; Arabic translation of recommendationss, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00010; Hansen, Greg
      Unnamed translator. An Arabic translation of the Recommendations section of the report "Coming to Terms with the Humanitarian Imperative in Iraq".
    - The US Citizen-Soldier and the Global War on Terror: The National Guard Experience, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00011; Minear, Larry
      Paper dated September, 2007. This report presents a composite picture of the impacts of the Global War on Terror on those who have fought it. It relies where possible on the troops own words, both citizen-soldiers and active-duty military personnel. Th e study focuses largely but not exclusively on the experiences of members in the National Guard, citizen-soldiers being a particularly illuminating bellwether of issues associated with the Global War on Terror. The core message is that the fi rst-hand experience of fighting in the Global War on Terrorfulfilling and satisfying for some, searing and traumatic for many, daunting and unsettling for mostraises issues of policy and practice that have only begun to be pondered. These include the high costspersonal and social, direct and indirect, financial and institutionalof the current approach to tackling terrorism, the need for more energetic efforts to re-integrate returning veterans into American society, the viability of continuing to respond to future threats of a divisive political nature with all-volunteer forces, and the future of the National Guard as an institution
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Terrorism; United States National Guard
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015 (HA 2015)-A Summary, 2006-09-18; UA197.001.DO.00012; Donini, Antonio
      Paper dated September 18, 2006. HA 2015 is a major independent research project based at the Alan Shawn Feinstein International Center at Tufts University in the US. It is an international effort involving researchers and consultants from a wide variety of countries. It focuses on the challenges and compromises that are likely to affect humanitarian action worldwide in the next decade.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015 (HA 2015)-A Summary; Arabic translation, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00013; Donini, Antonio
      Unnamed translator. An Arabic translation of the HA 2015 Summary.
    - The Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power, and Perceptions: Methodology for Field Research, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00014; Minear, Larry; Donini, Antonio
      Methodology for HA 2015 field research, including description of the project, survey for locals/focus groups, survey for professional aid workers, survey for others, a guide for focus groups, and an informed consent form.
    - Agenda Humanitaire a l'Horizon 2015: Principes, Pouvoir et Perceptions, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00015; GRIP; Feinstein International Center
      Report copyright 2006. French translation of the Preliminary Report. Translated by Groupe de Recherche et D'Information sur la Paix et la Securite
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: PowerPoint presentation in Kabul, Afghanistan, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00016; Donini, Antonio
      36 slides of overview of Feinstein International Center and HA 2015 research delivered to audience in Kabul.
    - A group of women in Kabul examine the HA2015 Preliminary Report, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00017; Donini, Antonio
      Image dated November, 2006. Caption: "The Feinstein International Center team reconvened some of the original focus groups to bring back the preliminary findings to those that provided the information."
    - Afghanistan: Humanitarianism Under Threat, 2009; UA197.001.DO.00018; Donini, Antonio
      Based on extensive field interviews in Afghanistan, this briefing paper is an update of a 2006 study on perceptions of humanitarian action in Afghanistan, which was part of the Humanitarian Agenda 2015 research program. The paper highlights critical issues affecting the provision of humanitarian action and suggests how they could, partially at least, be redressed. Building on data collected through interviews in the aid community as well as with ordinary Afghans, the briefing paper finds that humanitarianism is under deep threat in Afghanistan because of the perceived association of aid agencies with the US-led intervention. Humanitarian actors and the principles they profess are under attack. The ability of humanitarian agencies to address urgent need is compromised by internal and external factors, i.e., both by the organization and modus operandi of aid agencies on the ground, and by an extremely volatile and dangerous operating environment.The aid community in Afghanistan faces severe challenges that need to be urgently addressed so that civilians in need can be protected and assisted and the credibility of the humanitarian enterprise restored. Opportunities for more principled humanitarian action, by separating or insulating it from political and military agendas, should not be missed. Failure to do so will have dire consequences for Afghans and for the future of humanitarianism worldwide.
      Humanitarian Assistance
    - Afghanistan: Humanitarianism Unraveled?, 2010; UA197.001.DO.00019; Donini, Antonio
      This publication expands on the briefing paper on Afghanistan issued in March 2009, taking into account developments in the past year. It is based on some 40 interviews with UN and NGO aid agency staff, donors, a selection of Afghan government officials, and Afghan intellectuals and analysts in Kabul in January and March 2010. An earlier draft was circulated in Kabul in late March 2010 as an input into a workshop for aid agencies and donors hosted by ACBAR and supported by OFDA and UN-OCHA.
    - Humanitarian Futures Context Mapping, 2004-03-26; UA197.001.DO.00020; Feinstein International Center
      Humanitarian action and the diversity of actors and actions associated with the humanitarian label grew exponentially in the roughly fifteen years since the winding down of the Cold War. That growth brought tremendous opportunities, but also tremendous pressures on the humanitarian system and its inherent linkage of values to action. These strains have become even more apparent and in need of urgent attention, against the backdrop of the rapidly evolving international geopolitical landscape as played out in Afghanistan and Iraq.
      Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
    - The Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power and Perceptions, 2005-07-28; UA197.001.DO.00021; Feinstein International Center
      Issue briefs on forthcoming research
    - The Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power, and Perceptions (One Page Summary), 2005-11-11; UA197.001.DO.00022; Feinstein International Center
      Building on earlier Humanitarianism and War Project studies, the Feinstein International Famine Center at Tufts University is embarking on new independently-funded policy research, aimed at equipping the humanitarian enterprise to better address emerging challenges.
  - The Alchemy Project, 2001 -- 2004; UA197.002; 6 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports, studies and other materials from the Feinstein Center initiative "The Alchemy Project." This project related to refugee and forced migration issues in Africa.
    This series is arranged chronologically.
    - The Alchemy Project: Report of Actitivies Year One, 2001 -- 2002; UA197.002.002.00001; Jacobsen, Karen
      The Alchemy Project works in zones of protracted conflict and displacement in Africa to find ways to support the livelihoods of refugees and internally displaced people and the communities in which they live. We believe that supporting livelihoods is a sustainable and dignified way to assist displaced people and to benefit their host communities by developing local economies and reducing local conflict.
      Refugees; Finance; Conflict
    - The Alchemy Project: Report of Activities Year Two, 2002 -- 2003; UA197.002.002.00002; Jacobsen, Karen
    - The Alchemy Project: Strategic Plan and Operational Report, 2003-09-01; UA197.002.002.00003; Jacobsen, Karen
    - Alchemy Project Workshop Report: 'Lessons Learned From Livelihood Interventions In Conflict-Affected Areas', 2004; UA197.002.002.00004; Jacobsen, Karen
      A two-day workshop was held from 19-20 February 2004 by the Alchemy Project in Maputo, Mozambique, with implementing partner NGOs from Kenya, Guinea, South Africa, Zambia, Tanzania, Congo (DRC), Burundi and Mozambique. This workshop was organized and coordinated by Alchemy Project Director, Karen Jacobsen, chaired by Angela Raven Roberts (Feinstein International Famine Center), and was hosted by World Relief in Mozambique.
    - The Alchemy Project: Year Three Report, 2003 -- 2004; UA197.002.002.00005; Jacobsen, Karen
      This abbreviated report on our activities for Year 3, is intended to accompany the Final Report that describes all our accomplishments for three years and places these activities in the wider context of the Alchemy Project.
      Refugees; Conflict; Finance
    - The Alchemy Project: Final Report, 2001 -- 2004; UA197.002.002.00006; Jacobsen, Karen
  - Uganda: Upholding Rights in the Face of Violence, 2001 -- 2012; UA197.004; 14 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Uganda: Upholding rights in the face of violence project.
    - Angering Akuju: Survival and Suffering in Karamoja, 2008; UA197.004.004.00001; Stites, Elizabeth; Akabwai, Darlington; Mazurana, Dyan; Ateyo, Priscillar
      Karamoja is the poorest and least developed region of Uganda. The population experiences chronic food insecurity, little access to basic services, the weakening of traditional livelihood systems, ongoing insecurity, human rights violations and a near complete lack of law and order institutions. Armed raiding of livestock and associated loss of life and destruction of property are common and pervasive. Economic investment and development is minimal due to the threat of road ambushes and lack of transport and communication infrastructure. Attention to the region, however, on the part of national and international agencies, donors, and Ugandan legislators is growing. This field-based report provides an in-depth analysis of key aspects affecting livelihood strategies and human security in the region, as well as broad recommendations for local, national and international actors seeking to expand their knowledge, policies or programming in the Karamoja region.
      Conflict; Feinstein International Center
    - A Way Forward for Assisting Women and Girls in Northern Uganda, 2008; UA197.004.004.00002; Mazurana, Dyan; Carlson, Khristopher; Blattman, Chris; Annan, Jeannie
      Little is known about the short and long term effects of war on youth. Yet without an understanding of who is at risk of violence (and from whom), the factors that affect violence and acceptance, a sense of the long-term impacts of war violence, and a strong grasp of the factors that protect youth, how can we design more effective prevention, protection, rehabilitation and reintegration programs?
      Gender; Feinstein International Center
    - Assessing Uganda's cross-border pursuit of the Lord's Resistance Army, 2008; UA197.004.004.00003; Ochan, Clement
      Since 2002 the Ugandan army the Ugandan People's Defense Force (UPDF) has been operating inside South Sudan in pursuit of rebels from the Lord's Resistance Army (LRA). Joint operations with the Sudan People's Liberation Army (SPLA) which now rules the autonomous region have failed to dislodge the LRA, which has broadened its area of operations. After abandoning peace talks and refusing to surrender himself to the International Criminal Court, Joseph Kony, the LRA leader, has redeployed his forces over wide areas astride the borders of Sudan, Uganda, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, and the Central African Republic. The LRA continues to terrorize civilians. To date there has been little analysis of the role of the UPDF in South Sudan. Based on fieldwork in the two locations where the UPDF has been garrisoned Feinstein International Center researcher Clement Ochan produces evidence from Sudanese civilians and officials that the Ugandan military has failed to vigorously pursue the LRA. Civilians and officials alike allege the government of Uganda is spinning out the conflict which Uganda has presented as an integral part of the Global War on Terror in order to secure Western military assistance. Have ill-disciplined UPDF and SPLA soldiers been more interested in securing benefits for themselves than winning the war? Could the Dinka-dominated SPLA do more to protect members of minority communities many of whom did not necessarily support the struggle to liberate South Sudan from LRA attacks? This report informs the background to the current crisis in the region and discussions about whether local and international policy-makers should rely primarily on military force to protect civilians from the ongoing threat posed by the LRA.
      Conflict; Armaments; Feinstein International Center
    - Out-Human beings--Migrations, Return, and Resettlement in Karamoja, Uganda: The case of Kobulin, Bokora County, 2007-06-07; UA197.004.004.00004; Stites, Elizabeth; Mazurana, Dyan; Akabwai, Darlington
      As part of a larger project entitled "Livelihoods and Human Security in Karamoja," this briefing paper presents findings on causal factors and broad patterns in out-Human beings--Migrations among the Bokora population. The paper also seeks to provide context for the specific case study of the population picked up on the streets of Kampala and sent to a reception site at Kobulin in Bokora County of Moroto District. Using a gender and generational analysis, the briefing paper presents data on the main factors underlying out-Human beings--Migrations, the mechanics of this process, people's experiences in the cities, the return to Kobulin, and the population's current situation and hopes for the future.
      Human beings--Migrations; Feinstein International Center
    - Foraging and Fighting: Community Perspectives on Natural Resources and Conflict in Southern Karamoja, 2010-08-12; UA197.004.004.00005; Stites, Elizabeth; Fries, Lorin; Akabwai, Darlington
      This joint publication by the Feinstein International Center and Save the Children in Uganda examines the perspectives and experiences of communities in the southern Karamoja region of Uganda regarding natural resources and Conflict, Armed (War). The study set out to better understand local views on this topic in response to the assumption in policy circles that resource scarcity or competition drives the Conflict, Armed (War) in this pastoral and agro-pastoral area. We found that while sites of natural resource exploitation are often insecure, respondents in the study population did not attribute this to direct Conflict, Armed (War) over the resources themselves. Rather, violence is common in these locations because opposing groups are most likely to come into contact with each other at these sites. On the flip side, respondents stressed that peace allows for better sharing of resources and better management of resource scarcity in times of stress or hardship.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Natural resources; Human Security; Feinstein International Center
    - Forced Marriage within the Lord's Resistance Army, 2008-08-14; UA197.004.004.00006; Carlson, Khristopher; Mazurana, Dyan
      "Forced Marriage within the Lord's Resistance Army, Uganda" demonstrates that forced marriage includes acts codified as crimes in international customary and human rights law. These crimes include rape, sexual slavery, enforced pregnancy, forced labor, enslavement, and torture. However, the crime of forced marriage is unique from the above mentioned crimes, as it contains the element of forced conjugality.
      Conflict, Armed (War); forced marriage; Feinstein International Center
    - In Search of Security: A Regional Analysis of Armed Conflict in Northern Uganda, Eastern Uganda, and Southern Sudan, 2005-11-10; UA197.004.004.00007; Feinstein International Center
      The war and humanitarian crises engulfing northern Uganda are intricately linked with the armed Conflict, Armed (War) and unrest in eastern Uganda and southern Sudan. As a result of the links between the upheavals in these three areas, a vicious cycle of interlocked armed Conflict, Armed (War) and insecurity exists across the region. Yet the current policy of key international donor governments, the World Bank, the United Nations, and the African Union of addressing these Conflict, Armed (War)s in relative isolation may ultimately guarantee that armed Conflict, Armed (War) continues in the region. Regardless of the optimism surrounding the current peace agreement between the government of Sudan (GoS) and the Sudanese People's Liberation Movement/Army (SPLM/A), given the existing conditions on the ground, it is likely that this region will continue to be mired in violence and crises unless policymakers and donors adapt their perspective to take into account the larger regional picture.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Arms control; Feinstein International Center
    - Movement on the Margins: Livelihoods and Security in Kitgum District, 2006-11-09; UA197.004.004.00008; Stites, Elizabeth; Mazurana, Dyan; Carlson, Khristopher
      The protracted Conflict, Armed (War) in northern Uganda has created profound insecurity, brought the widespread loss of agrarian livelihoods, and pushed nearly two million people into internal Forced Human beings--Migrations camps. With the current cessation of hostilities between the rebel Lord's Resistance Army and the government of Uganda, many people are increasingly on the move in northern Uganda, whether moving in and out of camps on a daily or seasonal basis, moving between camps and semi-settled villages, or returning to their pre-war homes.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Feinstein International Center
    - Changing Roles, Shifting Risks: Livelihood Impacts of Disarmament in Karamoja, Uganda, 2009-07-15; UA197.004.004.00009; Stites, Elizabeth; Akabwai, Darlington
      This report is the result of the first phase of a partnership with Save the Children in Uganda. Based on field work conducted in April 2009 in Moroto and Kotido Districts, Changing Roles, Shifting Risks: Livelihood Impacts of Disarmament in Karamoja, Uganda examines the experiences and perceptions of communities of the present disarmament campaign carried out by the Uganda People's Defence Force and the Government of Uganda.
      Disarmament; Feinstein International Center
    - The State of Female Youth in Northern Uganda: Findings from the Survey of War Affected Youth, 2008-04-29; UA197.004.004.00010; Annan, Jeannie; Blattman, Christopher; Carlson, Khristopher; Mazurana, Dyan
      Youth have been both the primary victims and the primary actors in the twenty-two year war between the Government of Uganda and the Lord's Resistance Army. It was not clear, however, exactly who is suffering, how much, and in what ways. For instance, researchers knew little about the experience of youth: what is the magnitude, incidence, and nature of the violence, trauma, and suffering of youth in northern Uganda? An understanding of the effects of war on women and girls was particularly lacking, whether they were abducted or affected by the violence in other ways.
      Women; Children--Crimes against; Conflict, Armed (War); Feinstein International Center
    - Making Reintegration Work for Youth in Northern Uganda, 2001-11-23; UA197.004.004.00011; Annan, Jeannie; Blattman, Chris; Carlson, Khristopher; Mazurana, Dyan
      New survey data on war-affected youth suggest that past approaches and programs are insufficient to meet the needs of youth newly returning from the Lord's Resistance Army (LRA) as well as those who have already returned.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Children--Crimes against; Feinstein International Center
    - The Scramble for Cattle, Power and Guns in Karamoja, 2008-02-14; UA197.004.004.00012; Akabwai, Darlington; Ateyo, Priscillar E.
      This new report on the Karamoja Cluster of Uganda, Sudan, Kenya, and Ethiopia is the result of several years of field work by a respected Teso elder from the region with assistance from a Turkana woman. Dr. Akabwai, the lead author, has over thirty years of experience in the Karamoja Cluster, where he started working as a large animal veterinarian in the early 1970s. Based on his extensive contacts within local communities, Dr. Akabwai was able to gain access to privileged information on the weapons trade and cattle raiding that underpin the widespread insecurity across the larger region. Ms. Ateyo's participation in the research facilitated access to women of all ages. The result is a unique and thorough examination and analysis that includes gendered and generational perspectives.
      Arms control; Livestock; Feinstein International Center
    - Adaptation and Resilience: Responses to Changing Dynamics in Northern Karamoja, Uganda, 2010-11-19; UA197.004.004.00013; Stites, Elizabeth; Huisman, Carrie Stefansky